<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The celestial race a discourse perswading to the practice of celerity, constancy, &amp; sincerity in the ways of God : preached at the funeral of Mrs. Elizabeth Knack, daughter of Mr. Thomas Knack of Edgerton in Kent, who died January 2, Anno Dom. 1692 in the eleventh year of her age / by William Bush ...</title>
            <author>Bush, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30698</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B6232</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1534</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13069416</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13069416</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97103</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30698)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97103)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 409:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The celestial race a discourse perswading to the practice of celerity, constancy, &amp; sincerity in the ways of God : preached at the funeral of Mrs. Elizabeth Knack, daughter of Mr. Thomas Knack of Edgerton in Kent, who died January 2, Anno Dom. 1692 in the eleventh year of her age / by William Bush ...</title>
                  <author>Bush, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9], 64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Dunton ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682 [i.e. 1692]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Knack, Elizabeth, 1680 or 81-1692.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97103:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97103:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Celeſtial Race.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A DISCOURSE Perſwading to the PRACTICE OF Celerity, Conſtancy, &amp; Sincerity IN THE WAYS of GOD.</p>
            <p>Preached at the Funeral of Mrs. <hi>Elizabeth Knock,</hi> Daughter of Mr. <hi>Thomas Knock,</hi> of <hi>Edgerton</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> who died <hi>January</hi> 2. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1692. in the Eleventh year of her Age.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Buſh</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>Non dormentibus provenit regnum coelorum nec otio &amp; deſidiae torpentibus beatitudo aeternita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ingeritur. <bibl>
                  <hi>Proſp. de vi. contempl.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>John Dunton</hi> at the <hi>Raven</hi> in the <hi>Poultry.</hi> MDC<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>XCII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:97103:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97103:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Chriſtian Readers, Eſpecially the AUDITORS OF THIS SERMON.</head>
            <p>HAving now compli'd with the Deſires of thoſe that were the Hearers of this Diſcourſe, to make it Publick, I hope 'twill meet with that Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation
<pb facs="tcp:97103:3"/> as Diſcourſes of this Nature ſhould among Chriſtians. That the Subject might have been managed after a better manner, is not at all doubted of, but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged; and I hope the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der will be more favourable than to Cenſure me as Proud or Conceited of my own Labours, or Ambitious of appearing in Print; aſſuring you, I had not done it now, had it been poſſible for me fairly to have avoided it. And altho the manner after which the Subject is mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,
<pb facs="tcp:97103:3"/> be mean and deſpiſable, yet the Matter it ſelf may be uſeful (by the Bleſſing of the Almighty) to excite Slothful Chriſtians to a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diligence in their Duty; to reduce the wandring to the right way; to keep ſuch as are going on in the ways of God, from Apoſtatizing; and to diſcover and beat down that great ſin, <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy,</hi> that is ('tis to be fear'd) predominant in a great many ſeeming ſerious Christians, and in ſome as much unknown to themſelves
<pb facs="tcp:97103:4"/> as to others. If any object a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, becauſe of its plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, I hope this Anſwer will ſatisfy them; It was not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to pleaſe Perſons Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, but to profit their Souls; and I had rather be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, than admir'd. I now hope, Chriſtians, you will propoſe the ſame end to your ſelves in Reading, as I do in Writing, which is, That your Souls might receive be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and comfort hereby. I ſhall ſay no more, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech the God of all Grace to help and enable you ſo to run
<pb facs="tcp:97103:4"/> the Race that is ſet before you, that you may at laſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a Crown of Glory. And this I ſhall do particularly for you that were the Hearers of this Sermon, and that uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally attend upon my Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry. I conclude my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Souls Friend and Servant in the Goſpel of Chriſt Jeſus, W. BUSH.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:97103:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97103:5"/>
            <head>THE CELESTIAL RACE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1 COR. ix. 24. latter part.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>So run, that ye may obtain.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>VVHEN we ſeriouſly reflect upon the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of our Dy ng, and the uncertainty of the time when; when we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der too, that the longeſt time of living is but ſhort, ſo ſhort, that if it were well improved in working out our Salvation, we ſhould find very few ſpare minutes; or that we had too much, we ſhould ſeldom be heard to complain. I ſay, when we ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97103:6"/> conſider of theſe things, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we ſhall be mov'd to a greater diligence in preparing for Eternity, in making ready our Accounts, in running ſwiftly the Race that is ſet before us, leſt Death overtake us as we are loytering, and ſtop us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Courſe be finiſhed, and then we are eternally undone. I therefore pray and beſeech you, in the Name of my Maſter Chriſt, not only to give ſerious Attention to this ſeaſonable Exhortation that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle gives you in my Text, but alſo to make it your practice ſo to run, as to obtain.</p>
            <p>In the former part of the verſe, the Apoſtle borroweth a Similitude from thoſe that run a Terreſtial Race for a Temporary Reward; that as in that Race, tho many run, yet 'tis only he that out-runs the reſt that perſevereth to the end, that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains the Prize; even ſo in the Race of Godlineſs, none ſhall be crown'd, but thoſe that hold out to the end of their lives. Yet, notwithſtanding,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97103:6"/> there is this difference in this Simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, In the Race Terreſtial, he only is rewarded that cometh firſt to the Mark; but in the Race Celeſtial, not only one, but all that run lawfully, ſhall obtain.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine that I ſhall (by the aſſiſtance of the Almighty) diſcourſe of from the words, is this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the greateſt Speedineſs and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerity in the ways of God, muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly practiſed by thoſe that would ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain everlaſting Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Method that I ſhall follow in ſpeaking to this Doctrine, will be this,</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall give you Reaſons for the proof of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Shew you how you may fit and prepare your ſelves to run ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily and ſwiftly in this heavenly Race.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:97103:7"/>3. Speak of the Reward impli'd in my Text, which will be certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly given to thoſe that run lawfully. And,</p>
            <p n="4">4. And laſtly, Apply it.</p>
            <p>That thoſe that run in this heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Race, muſt run ſwiftly and ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, I ſhall prove by theſe three Reaſons.</p>
            <p>The firſt may be drawn from the celerity, brevity, and uncertainty of our Lives, which here in my Text, is compar'd to a Race for ſwiftneſs in paſſing away; for <hi>ſo run that ye may obtain,</hi> is as if the Apoſtle had ſaid, So live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel of Chriſt Jeſus, that ye may obtain Life everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The Life of Man is always (in Scripture) compared to ſuch things as denote the celerity, the brevity, and the uncertainty of it; ſometimes 'tis compar'd to a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, as <hi>Pſalm</hi> 109.23. ſometimes to a vapour, as <hi>James</hi> 4.14. <hi>that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97103:7"/> for a little time, and then vaniſhes away. Job</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 9.20.</note> conſidering the ſwift paſſage of mans Life, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth it to the ſwift motion of the Eagle when haſting to her prey; or the ſwift Ships on the Waters; that which is of leaſt duration, and of moſt ſpeedy paſſage, may be a fit Compariſon of the Life of Man; the youngeſt, and the ſtrongeſt in a very ſhort ſpace muſt be removed hence. Active Youth is quickly metamorphoſed into crooked Age; ſo frail and uncertain are our lives, that for ought we know, one week, or day, or hour, yea, perhaps one moment more, may put a period to them. We have daily Examples of the uncertainty of the time of our departure hence; we ſee one cut down in his early Spring, and in his blooming greener Youth, and his Sun is covered with Darkneſs, almoſt as ſoon as it begins to riſe, whilſt another weathers out the Storms, and grows to a mature and full Age. One does but peep as it
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97103:8"/> were into the World, takes a ſhort view of it, and is commanded out again; and is at his Journeys end in the morning of his Life; and another is allowed to travel till the ſhadows of the Evening are ſtretched out, according to their moſt regular Advances, and till the threeſcore and ten, that is the uſual date of long Life, is expired. One is quickly ſummon'd to the great Tribunal and judged, whilſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther has a longer ſpace wherein to prepare for his Tryal,<note place="margin">Vid. Mr: <hi>Roger</hi>'s Practical Diſcourſe of Sickneſs and Reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, <hi>page 13.</hi>
               </note> and his final Doom. You may now, for ought you know, be hearing of your laſt Sermon, and offer up now your laſt Prayer, and have no other op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity than this that you now enjoy, to prepare and make ready for Eternity, but be immediately ſummoned to appear at the Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of God, to render an Account to him of all your publick and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Actions, for all that you have ever thought, ever ſpoke, or done; for all the Talents, the Time, the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97103:8"/> Mercies, the Health, the Strength, the Opportunities, and the Seaſons, and Days of Grace that you ever had; for all the Evil that you might have avoided; for all the Good that you might have done, and did not, and all this before that Judge, who has beheld your ways from your Birth to the Grave;<note place="margin">Vid. Mr. <hi>Roger</hi>'s Practical Diſcourſe of Sickneſs and Reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, <hi>page 49.</hi>
               </note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that Judge who cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, and who will not be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon. And is there not then a neceſſity of being ſpeedy in your Courſe? Do you apprehend ſo much as one minute to loyter in, ſeeing you know not whether you may live ſo ſmall a ſpace of time longer? And when this Life is end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, our work is done, for after this Life there will be no place for Pardon, nor ſpace for Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; <hi>There is no work,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 9.10.</note> 
               <hi>nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, nor knowledg, nor wiſdom in the grave whither we are all going.</hi> Therefore muſt we be ſpeedy in the ways of God, becauſe the time of our lives (which is all the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97103:9"/> time we have) is ſo ſhort, ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, and haſting away ſo faſt from us.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Reaſon may be drawn from the great Work that we have to do in this little time. How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Corruptions have we to ſubdue, and Luſts to mortify, and Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations to reſiſt? What loads of Sin yet lye upon many of us unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, becauſe unrepented of? What ſubtil, politick, powerful Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies have we to engage with, ſuch as the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil? The World is daily entice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of us with its Pleaſures, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, or Honours, perſwading us to place our Affections upon theſe fading Vanities, and to accept of its favours, which, alas, are but as the Salutes of an Enemy; and yet how hard is it for the beſt of God's People to keep themſelves from the Pollutions of it! That it is ſo, our own daily Experience teacheth us; and yet this ſo enticing an Enemy we muſt keep our ſelves from the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97103:9"/> loving of; for if any Man love the World, <hi>i. e.</hi> with a predominant Love, or the <hi>things that are in the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 John 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>the love of the Father is not in him.</hi> A ſecond Enemy is the Fleſh, which always murmurs at Subjection, and is at continual va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance with the Spirit;<note place="margin">Gal. 5.17.</note> and there is great difficulty in overcoming ſo near a Foe: This was it, that made that great Apoſtle, <hi>volens nolens,</hi> become a Captive.<note place="margin">Rom. 7.19</note> 
               <hi>Caeſar</hi> being once ask'd, What was the moſt difficult thing to overcome in this Life? Anſwered, <hi>Seipſum vincere,</hi> to overcome himſelf and his untamed Affections. The third is the Devil, called, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Vid. Leigh's Crit. Sacra. <hi>p. 235.</hi>
               </note> from the <hi>Hebrew</hi> word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah,</hi> which is <hi>Adverſarius,</hi> an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary; he is really the impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable Enemy of our Souls, and joyns his Aſſiſtance to the World and Fleſh, that ſo by one means or other he might deſtroy us; this is he that tempts ſo ſubtilly, ſo frequently, that we muſt, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97103:10"/> ought to be always prepared for him; and unleſs we are furniſhed with the whole Armour of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. from 13. to 18.</note> 'tis impoſſible for us to withſtand him; ſo ſubtil and potent is he, that the holieſt Souls, at ſome time or other, have been overcome by him. Now, what great reaſon is there for us to uſe the greateſt ſpeed we can, that have not only ſo little time, and ſo much work to do in it, but alſo ſuch ſubtil and potent Enemies to contend with, and to overcome? Well might the Apoſtle ſay<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil. 2.12.</hi> Non dicit Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolus nude <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſed <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, id eſt, accuratè magnoque cum ſtudio operamini. <hi>Chryſ.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>Work</hi> (not play, or idle) <hi>out your ſalvation with fear and trembling.</hi> Well may the Church of God be called <hi>Eccleſia Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litans,</hi> ſeeing it has ſo many, and ſo great Enemies, continually to engage with.</p>
            <p>A third, and laſt, may be drawn from Example: Thoſe that run an earthly Race, tho but for a mean Reward, what pains do they take, how extremely do they ſtrain them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that they may run ſwiftly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97103:10"/> to obtain? And ſhall we that run the Celeſtial Race (and that for ſo great a Reward as Heaven is) run ſlowly? Shall they take greater pains, and be more ſwift and ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for a periſhing Reward, than we for an eternal one? God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid! The Sun too, may be an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to us in this reſpect, <hi>Which is as a bridegroom coming out of his chamber,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm 19.5.</note> 
               <hi>and rejoyceth as a ſtrong man to run his race.</hi> And not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is the Sun an Example to us, but alſo our Lord himſelf, who whilſt he was in the World, was never idle: He wrought <hi>the works of him that ſent him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.4.</note> 
               <hi>while it was day.</hi> He left the boſome of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and came into the World, and became Man, and was like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Man in all things, Sin only excepted; overcame Death and Hell, fulfill'd the Law of God, and ſatisfied his Juſtice for us, appeaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Wrath againſt us, and has purchaſed for his People, by his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97103:11"/> Death, Everlaſting Life. Thus was all his time vigorouſly employ'd in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming the work he came about; well might the Church compare him (for his ſwiftneſs) <hi>to a Roe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>or a young Hart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have I prov'd, That Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerity and Speed in the ways of God, muſt of neceſſity be practiſed by thoſe that would obtain Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Life. And that, <hi>Firſt,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the ſhortneſs of our Lives, and their ſpeedy paſſing away from us; ſo ſoon are our days done, that if we are not ſpeedy, they will be gone before our work be done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Becauſe of the great work we have to do in this little time, which is ſo great, that we have need of more, rather than ſpare (for Sin and Vanity) any of that we have.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Becauſe of the Examples of Swiftneſs and Speedineſs, that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97103:11"/> we have, not only of Perſons that run with the greateſt ſpeedineſs an earthly Race, for the fading Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of the World; and of the Sun; but alſo of our Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who was moſt ſpeedy in work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out our Redemption, and ought to be imitated of all Chriſtians. For every Action of Chriſt ought to be inſtruction unto us,<note place="margin">Omnis Chriſti a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio, noſtra debet eſſe inſtructio. <hi>Gregor. Joh. 14.6.</hi>
               </note> he hath left us an Example; let us therefore tread in his ſteps, <hi>who is the way, the truth, and the life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this Celerity, this Speedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the ways of God muſt be conſtantly and continually practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed without giving over, and that to the end of your lives; for begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning well in the ways of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, is nothing, unleſs perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance be reſolv'd; for as thoſe that run a Race, tho they run never ſo directly, never ſo ſwiftly, ſhall not obtain the prize unleſs they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere to the end of it, even ſo if we continue not in the ways of God
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97103:12"/> to the end of our lives, we ſhall miſs of Heaven. The Soldier is not rewarded with Spoil, till he hath obtain'd the Victory, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall we be crown'd, till we have been more than Conquerors in Chriſt Jeſus.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.37.</note> Should you live in the Profeſſion of the Goſpel for many years, and at laſt prove Apoſtates, you would miſs of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; 'tis none but thoſe that endure to the end that ſhall be ſaved;<note place="margin">Matth. 10.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and yet notwithſtanding, there are many that are guilty in this reſpect; this Age abounds with ſhort-winded Profeſſors, that are eager for a ſpurt, and then give over; that for fear of Affliction, or Reproach, or the Impair of their Credit, or Eſteem in the World; nay, ſome ſuch Fools there are, (for I can call them by no fitter Name) that for a Scoff, or a Jeer, will turn back, will carry the Lord his Livery home again, and will wear it no longer: But it had been
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97103:12"/> better for ſuch, that they had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver known the ways of God, than thus to depart from them; nay, it had been better that they had never been born, for God ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hors Apoſtates with his Soul;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38.</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if you would obtain Heaven, pull not your Necks out of Chriſts Yoak, keep forward, give not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver upon any account; but the very firſt ſtep you take in the ways of Godlineſs, reſolve (by the aſſiſtance of Divine Grace) to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere to the end of your Lives, for it muſt (you ſee) of neceſſity be done. Remember <hi>Lot</hi>'s Wife, who for looking back was turn'd into a Pillar of Salt, for an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to all thoſe that hereafter ſhould turn their backs upon God. Let the Apoſtle, therefore, be our Pattern in this reſpect,<note place="margin">Phil. 3 14.</note> 
               <hi>To preſs for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward towards the mark for the prize of the high calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:97103:13"/>
            <p>Having thus prov'd the Doctrine, I proceed to the ſecond particular, namely, to ſhew you how you may fit and prepare your ſelves to run ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily and ſwiftly in this Heavenly Race.</p>
            <p>If therefore you would be fitted and prepared to run ſpeedily and ſwiftly in the ways of God, obſerve theſe three things:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Avoid wicked Company, which has been the ruin of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a Soul. When Conſcience is once thoroughly awakened, and Perſons come to be convinced of the Soul-deſtroying Nature of their Sins, amongſt other their complaints, do we not ſometimes hear them utter ſuch as theſe; O that I had never known the Names, nor ſeen the Faces of ſuch and ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons! Theſe were they that enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced me to Sin, to ruin my Soul; theſe were they that taught me to ſpeak the Language of Hell; theſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97103:13"/> were they that taught me to damn, and to ſink my own, and others precious Souls; theſe were they (that by the help of the Devil, and my own corrupt Inclinations) made me in love with all manner of Iniquity, and to hate the thoughts of Piety, and living to my Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor and God; theſe were they that made me out of love with the ways of Holineſs, and to become an utter Enemy to thoſe that walk in them; theſe were they that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged me in every thing that was offenſive to the Almighty, in every thing that might further the ruin of my poor Soul; to deſpiſe the Counſel of my Godly Parents, Relations, and Friends; to mock at the wholſome Inſtructions of Gods Miniſters, and to laugh and jeer at Hell and Damnation. O that I ſhould adhere to their deviliſh Counſel! O that I ſhould be ſo eaſily drawn away to my own ruin! I ſay, are not theſe ſometimes the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97103:14"/> complaints of many poor Souls? And who is able to expreſs the Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows they undergo upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, before their Comfort comes, if not, go mourning to their Graves. O conſider when you are gaming, or ſwearing, or drinking to exceſs, or profaning the Lords day, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with your wicked Companions, how unlikely you are to make haſte to Heaven, when you are going in the ready way that leads to Hell. Now this I would have all take ſpecial notice of, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially young Perſons, for they are more ſubject to be drawn away; the green Twig is eaſily bent; O young Perſons, I beſeech you (if you would run with ſpeed in the ways of God) take heed of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Company; though they entice you never ſo frequently, never ſo ſtrongly; like thoſe, <hi>Proverbs</hi> 1. from 11. to 15. though they pretend never ſuch Friendſhip and Love; Yet, as one ſays, never count them
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97103:14"/> your Friends, nor ſuch as will do you any kindneſs, that would lead you to Sin, the Devil, and Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Though they tell you of time enough when you are old, to ſeek after Heaven and Happineſs, and that 'tis Folly and Madneſs, to ſpend the prime of your time in ſeeking for uncertainties, and bringing your ſelves to ſuch a Courſe of Life, as deprives you of all Comfort, Delight, and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; though they endeavour to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you from going forward, by telling you of Lions in the way, and would have you turn back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and Sin your ſelves to Hell with them; and endeavour to ſtay you ſo long till you have not time enough (ſhould you be never ſo ſpeedy) to reach your Journeys end, yet hearken to none of their Deluſions, bid defiance to them all. As to their perſwading you to let alone your Repentance till old Age; tell them, late Repentance is ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97103:15"/> ſafe. Tell them there's no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that God ſhould accept of the lame and rotten Service of your old Age, when you have given the prime of your ſtrength to the Devil. Therefore take <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Counſel,<note place="margin">Prov. 1.10. <hi>and</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>My Son, if ſinners entice thee, conſent thou not. My ſon, walk not thou in the way with them, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frain thy feet from their path.</hi> It was not lawful for a <hi>Jew</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with a <hi>Samaritane,</hi> neither might the <hi>Hebrew</hi> eat with the <hi>Egyptian,</hi> but it was accounted abominable; neither is it lawful for us that are going to Heaven to be the Familiars of thoſe that are going to Hell. <hi>We are commanded to withdraw our ſelves from thoſe that walk diſorderly,</hi> 2 Theſſal. 3.6. I beſeech you therefore a ſecond time (particularly young ones) to abandon ſuch, for they will great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impede and hinder you in your way:<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.63.</note> O be like the <hi>Pſalmiſt, A companion of all them that fear the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97103:15"/> Lord, and that keep his precepts;</hi> Theſe will further you in your way, and excite you to be ſpeedy in your Courſe, and encourage you by helping of you forward all they can, and accompany you in your way, which will be great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. But ſo much as to the firſt particular, namely, That if we would run with ſpeedineſs in the ways of God, we muſt avoid wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Company, which if we do not, will be a very great, yea, a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual, if not an eternal hindrance to us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> If we would be prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to run ſpeedily and ſwiftly in this heavenly Race, we muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loaded of the things of this World. Perſons that run a Terreſtrial Race diveſt themſelves of their Garments, that they may run more ſwiftly; ſo if we would run ſwiftly in the ways of Holineſs, we muſt be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burdened ſo far of the things of this World, as that they may not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pede
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97103:16"/> our courſe, or make us run ſlowly; ſome are ſo cumber'd with the world that they can't wag a foot towards Heaven; and others ſo clogg'd that if they do go at all, 'tis very heavily, hardly ſet one foot before another, as we ſay: O how do they ſuffer the world to take up ſo much of their precious time,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Gouges</hi> Word to Sinners, &amp;c. page 135.</note> that they can ſcarce find any leiſure either for Cloſet-devotions, or Family-Prayers, but make their Religion give place to their world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly buſineſſes. And when at any time they fall upon the performance of Holy Duties, how are their hearts at that very time taken up with worldly thoughts, and imaginations; ſo that inſtead of converſing with God in his Holy Ordinances, and enjoying Communion with him therein, they converſe with the world, and hold Communion with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. Too many there are whoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions tell us, that they have no time to pray in their Families, no
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97103:16"/> time to inſtruct their Children and Servants in the things of God; no time to think of God, nor of their Duty to him; much leſs to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it; no time to prepare for Death and Eternity, nor to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the ſtate of their poor Souls. Surely ſuch as theſe will not dare to make ſuch a plea at the Bar of God, when he ſhall ask them, Why did you not obey my Commands, and obſerve to do my pleaſure? Why did you not take care of your Souls, and mind Eternity by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring for it? I ſay ſurely ſuch as theſe dare not reply, Lord, we had no time, which is in effect to ſay, Lord, we ſpent ſo much time in Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for Earth, that we had no time to Trade for Heaven: We had ſo much buſineſs in the Shop, that we could not frequent our Cloſets much: In truth, Lord, we had ſo much love for the things of the world, that we had none for thee nor our poor ſouls. Good God!
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97103:17"/> what will be the ſtate of ſuch ſouls! ſurely, if there may be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted degrees of torments in a place of ſuch miſery as Hell is, theſe muſt have the hotteſt there. Now 'tis love to the world that makes perſons ſo eager after it; if they did not love the world and the things thereof, they would not ſpend ſo much time and pains in ſeeking after the vanities thereof; and 'tis this that makes you right world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, for 'tis not the bare having, or poſſeſſing of the things of this world that makes you ſuch. Now 'tis impoſſible for thoſe to run ſpeedily and ſwiftly in the ways of God, that have placed their affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions on the world; a worldling may make, indeed, a fair profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſhew great forwardneſs, and ſpeedineſs in the ways of God, like the rich young man,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Mat. 19.20, 21, 22.</note> but when it comes to this, That their worldly enjoyments muſt be parted with, if they would keep themſelves in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97103:17"/> God's ways; if they would run ſo as to obtain, which is ſpeedily, why then they leave going any farther, and are with him, ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly ſorry, that Heaven can't be had at cheaper rates, ſo that their love to God and his ways is but from the teeth outward, as we ſay; 'tis no more than what may ſerve their intereſt in the world; ſo that in reality, the world is their God, their treaſure is here, and their hearts muſt of neceſſity be here too,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.21.</note> 
               <hi>for where the treaſure is, there will the heart be alſo.</hi> O therefore, whatever we have of the things of this world, let us not ſet our hearts upon them, let us not incumber our ſelves ſo much with them, as to let them take up all, or ſo much of our time, as to have none (or not enough) to ſpare for, to ſeek after (ſo as to obtain) Heaven: let us no longer ſo love the world, nor the things of it, as to ſuffer it to keep us
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97103:18"/> back,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Mr. <hi>Roger</hi>'s Pract. Diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>courſe of Sickn. and Recov. pa. 226, 227.</note> or to hinder us in our run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this Heavenly race. Let us not paint it with more alluring Colours, leſt we be ſtill more in love with it, and more loth to leave it; for ſhall we more eaſily part with things ſumptuous and ſplendid, than with things that are meaner and leſs ſuited to a fleſhly mind and life? We are Pilgrims, and ſhall we be ſo induſtrious to plant, and build, and ſow in a ſtrange Country, when we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs we are diſtant from our home? What man would ſet himſelf to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn his Inn, from which he may diſlodg the next morning, and it may be never ſee it any more? Surely the fadingneſs of the things of this world, might make us out of love with them: You may be rich and honourable to day, and by the morrow, Beggars. He that ſeriouſly conſiders of the many and great enjoyments that <hi>Job</hi> was poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with,<note place="margin">Job 1.</note> and how ſoon he was
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97103:18"/> depriv'd of all, and brought to the Dunghill, certainly can ſay no more of this world and things of it, than what the Wiſeman ſays,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.2</note> 
               <hi>Vanity of vanities, vanity of vanities, all is vanity.</hi> Why ſhould ſick Dreams run away with our hearts?<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Gale</hi>'s Serm. in the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plem. to the Morn. Exerciſe, &amp;c.</note> what are all thoſe things your hearts luſt after, but the ſcum, froth, droſs, and refuſe of the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Ah poor fools! why are your hearts ſo much bewitch'd with theſe night-viſions, whoriſh Idols, or curſed nothings of time? Remember how dear you pay for your beloved Idols, how much they are ſalted with the curſe of God. What fools are we to ſuffer our ſelves to be hindred in our way to Heaven, by and for ſuch things as are of ſo ſhort a durati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and continuance. Were the things of this world never ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, delightful and profitable, yet the conſideration of their ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy paſſing away, ſhould be, (one
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97103:19"/> would think) an argument ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to wean our love from them, and to keep us from ſuffering any thing of the world to ſtop or hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us in running our race. 'Twas a great ſaying of that <hi>Janſeniſt, I would never begin to love that, which one day I muſt ceaſe to love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3ly. And laſtly, As we muſt be unladen without, ſo we muſt alſo be empty within: Now that which clogs us within, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders us from running ſpeedily in the ways of God, is ſin; this is a dead weight to the ſoul, and 'tis impoſſible for you to take one right ſtep towards Heaven, (much leſs to run with ſpeed) whilſt you remain in a ſtate of ſin. For while you are in ſuch a ſtate, you are in a dead ſtate,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi> Pra. Diſco. of Sickn. and Reco. p. 114.</note> you taſte not the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, nor hear his loudeſt Calls; you tremble not at his moſt dreadful threats, neither are you drawn with his love, nor ſtart at
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97103:19"/> his approaching wrath. Your ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance has deprived your ſouls of all knowledg of your own miſeries; you are in a ſtate of death and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibility; and your caſe is the more ſad, becauſe you are like to fall under the power of eternal death; and though your temporal life is prolonged for a ſeaſon, yet we may ſay of you as of Malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors under the ſentence of the Law for their crimes, They are dead men, though there be a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieve, or a delay of execution for a little ſpace. You may as well expect a dead Corpſe to go or run, as expect ſuch as are in a ſtate of ſin, to do ſo in this Heavenly race. Or a perſon loaded with a burden, that he is ſcarce able to ſtand un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to be as ſpeedy in going, as one that hath no burden at all. And although perſons in a ſtate of unregeneracy and ſin, are not ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible what a burden ſin is; that it will ſink 'em to Hell if it be not
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97103:20"/> remov'd; yet when once Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is awakned, they will then ſay of their ſins as <hi>David</hi> did of his, <hi>as an heavy burden they are too heavy for me;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 38.4.</note> too heavy for me to bear long; ſo heavy, that if Infinite mercy doth not eaſe nor releaſe me, I muſt fall under it. If the yoke of Chriſt be eaſie,<note place="margin">Mat. 11.30.</note> and his burden light, than of neceſſity on the contrary, muſt the yoke of the Devil, which is ſin, be uneaſie, heavy, and intollerable to be born; and yet how many are there, that by the courſe of their lives ſeem to be of the opinion, that 'tis poſſible for them (notwithſtanding the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of their ſins) to be ſpeedy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in the ways of God, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Heaven; that their external profeſſion (without any ſuch thing as repentance and a holy life) will ſave them; but O how greatly will they be miſtaken! no doubt but there are many in Hell, that have heard and pray'd as much,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97103:20"/> or more than ever you have done. Thus you ſee how great a burden ſin is, and how vaſt a hinderance 'tis to you in your way; nay, ſuch a weight and burden is ſin, that it will hinder you from ever obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Heaven, if it be not remov'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore death. O therefore endeavour to get rid of this burden; loath, deteſt, and abhor ſin, becauſe God doth loath, deteſt, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor you for ſin; becauſe it ſeeks the utter ruin of your precious ſouls; beg of God to make you ſenſible that ſin is a burden, and then when you feel the weight of it, you will not be unwilling to part with it; beſeech him to quicken you <hi>who are dead in treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes and ſins;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 2.1.</note> plead with him earneſtly to make you ſincerely willing to part with your whole burden, with all your ſins; for every ſin muſt be left,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Gouges</hi> Word to Sinners, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 167.</note> or you had as good keep them all. Can you let all your ſins go but this one?
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97103:21"/> even this muſt go too, or your life muſt go for it: O ſet your ſelves againſt every ſin, great and ſmall, open and ſecret, carnal and ſpiritual; ſet your ſelves againſt them heartily; be willing to proſper and overcome; and ſet upon them ſpeedily; let not iniquity live a day longer, nor ſleep a night more in quiet with you. O let not that which is ſo much your hinderance, be retain'd by you; let God ſee your weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſin, by your earneſtneſs to be rid of it; and the great ſenſe you have of the impoſſibility of getting to Heaven with it; that ſo by patient continuing in your Duty, you may at laſt have a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous releaſe.</p>
            <p>I ſhould now ſpeak of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward imply'd in my Text; but before I do this, give me leave to ſpeak of one thing that is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of your ſtricteſt Obſervation;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97103:21"/> the Apoſtle does not ſay, in my Text, ſeem ſo to run as to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; or make an outward ſhew of running; but <hi>ſo run that ye may obtain;</hi> now, in thus expreſſing of himſelf, he excludes all Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, and counterfeit Godlineſs; and there is great reaſon for his doing thus. For in the viſible Church, 'tis certain, that there are many that outwardly profeſs Chriſt, but inwardly and with their heart de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny him; that are Chriſtians by Name, but not ſuch indeed. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Hypocrites there are, like paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Sepulchers, fair without, but within nothing but rottenneſs. Here then let me put you upon Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, whether or no you are not of this number? Hypocriſy is ſpun of a very fine Thread,<note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Biſhop</hi> Sander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon<hi>'s Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> 1. ad populum, <hi>p.</hi> 175.</note> and is not eaſily diſcernable without very diligent Examination; and things are not to be meaſured by the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhew, or by the Lump and Bulk, but by an exacter Rule,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97103:22"/> whether they be true or no: doſt thou bewail thy Sins with Tears? Doſt thou avoid groſs Sins with care? Doſt thou oppoſe againſt common Corruptions with zeal? Why all this thou mayeſt do, and yet be a Hypocrite.<note place="margin">Page 172.</note> Nay, you may, as the ſame Author ſays, be touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a deep feeling of your Sins, and with heavy Hearts and many Tears confeſs and bewail them, and not only promiſe, but alſo purpoſe amendment; you may be ſuperfici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally affected with, and find ſome overly comfort and refreſhing from the Contemplation of thoſe graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous promiſes of Mercy, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation, and Salvation, which are contained in the glorious Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; and have ſome degrees of perſwaſion that theſe promiſes are true, and ſome flaſhes of Confidence withal of your own perſonal Intereſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; all this and much more may you do, and yet be rotten (as he
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:97103:22"/> ſays) at Heart; wholly carnal and unrenewed, quite empty of ſound Faith, and Repentance, and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and every good Grace; full of damnable Pride and Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, as you may ſee Examples in <hi>Saul</hi>'s care for the deſtroying of Witches; in <hi>Jehu</hi>'s zeal in killing;<note place="margin">1 Sam. 28.3. 2 Kings 10.16, 28. Mark 6.20. 1 Kings 21.27.</note> 
               <hi>Baal</hi>'s Worſhippers; in <hi>Herod</hi>'s hearing of <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> gladly, and doing many things too; in <hi>Ahab</hi>'s Repentance and Humiliation. O therefore look to your hearts, be willing to know what they are, and don't play the Hypocrite with your Souls! Conſider, there's no Sin more odious in the ſight of God than this.<note place="margin">Simulata ſanctitas, eſt duplex iniquitas.</note> You ſhall never enter Heaven notwithſtanding all your Prayers and Tears, if you are Hypocrites. When you ſhall plead for Mercy at the Day of Judgment, Chriſt will tell you,<note place="margin">Matth. 7.23.</note> he knows you not. May I a little al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo gloſs upon your Miſery when you come to Hell, which will be
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:97103:23"/> moſt intollerable; you will ſhare in the greateſt of them. The looſe and prophane Wretches that lived like Devils Incarnate in the World, that ſpent very little or no time in Prayer, or Hearing, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Duties, and that took you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways for Saints, becauſe of your ſeeming ſtrictneſs in the ways of God, when they ſhall ſee you in the ſame dreadful Condition with themſelves, 'twill make them (if 'twere poſſible) laugh in Hell, to ſee that this is the end of your Profeſſion, of your ſtrictneſs in the ways of God, of your praying, and hearing, and the like; this will greatly aggravate your Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. O therefore, for Chriſts ſake, and the ſake of your own precious Souls, beware of Hypocriſy. I would (had I time) have given you ſome particular Marks of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy; at preſent then make but this out clearly, That Hypocriſy is not predominant in you, but that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:97103:23"/> in ſimplicity and ſincerity of heart (and not with fleſhly Wiſdom) you have your Converſations in the World; you may then be ſure you are not in the number of thoſe Hypocrites that ſhall be baniſhed for ever from the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord, and turned into Hell.</p>
            <p>I now return to my third and laſt Doctrinal head, namely, to ſpeak of the Reward implied in my Text, which ſhall be certainly given to thoſe that run lawfully, that run thus ſpeedily and ſwiftly, conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſincerely in this Heavenly Race; and this Reward is no other, nor can be no better than Heaven it ſelf;<note place="margin">Luke 12.32.</note> 
               <hi>'Tis your Fathers good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to give you the kingdom.</hi> Now, to ſpeak fully of this glorious place, and the Felicities that God hath prepared there for his People, is impoſſible; we are not able fully to conceive of them; therefore what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:97103:24"/> I may now ſpeak concerning the Glories, the Felicities of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; if you ever come there, you will ſay, behold the thouſand part was not told me; but according to what diſcoveries the Holy Ghoſt hath made of it in Scripture, we may ſpeak of it, and we may ſee the Glories of it ſet forth to us, by the diverſity and greatneſs of the Names thereof, and the Society we ſhall there enjoy. I ſhall ſpeak to two or three of the Names thereof briefly.</p>
            <p n="1">1. 'Tis called the Kingdom of God and Chriſt,<note place="margin">Revel. 12.10. Luke 23.42.</note> becauſe Chriſt having overcome Death, Hell, and Damnation, together with all the Enemies that did oppoſe and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us in our way to Heaven, doth rule there, and govern his Church Triumphant with Heavenly Peace, and Everlaſting Tranquility.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Beverly</hi>'s Great Soul of Man, <hi>p. 278.</hi>
               </note> If we could imagine, as indeed we cannot, becauſe experience ſo migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:97103:24"/> contradicts it, that any Prince ſhould live in all thoſe delights and pleaſures the moſt ſpendid Court affords, without any tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, or ſatiety ten thouſand years; what a dark Repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were this of this Kingdom, tho he could do, and enjoy all he would.</p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis call'd by the Name of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice,<note place="margin">Luke 23.43.</note> in reſpect of the abundant plenty of the greateſt of Pleaſures which the Saints can either wiſh for, or deſire.</p>
            <p n="3">3. 'Tis call'd Eternal Life,<note place="margin">Joh. 3.15. Matth. 25.46.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there ſhall be no more Death, nor Lamentation, nor Sorrow: We ſhall quit a vale of Tears, for Rivers of Eternal Pleaſures;<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Silve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi>'s Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in the Supplement to the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe.</note> an Element of Joys ſucceeds our bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Cup; our Rights can never be invaded there, nothing can ſtain the Comforts of that World; no Blots nor Wounds are there contracted
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97103:25"/> or endured; no Troubles in that <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el;</hi> there are no pauſes of Aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment through ſurpriſals of Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; Death ſmites no Corners there; Providence makes no Storms; there lies that Ark wherein no vile or wicked <hi>Cham</hi> ſhall dwell; the Glory of that place it knows no Eclipſe, nor Cloud, no dim Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries, or flat Notes ſhall be the Exerciſe or Entertainment of that State. I might give you more Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations upon the great and glorious Names of this Kingdom, but this may ſerve as a taſt of the Glories, the Joys of that bleſſed place, by which you may diſcern the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy théreof.</p>
            <p>But now as to the Society that there we ſhall enjoy. There we ſhall have the Company of God and Chriſt, Saints and Angels, and all our Godly Friends and Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and joyn with them in ſinging Hallelujahs to the Lord God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:97103:25"/> and to the Lamb his Son, that ſits upon the Throne for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.<note place="margin">Vid. Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi>'s Practical Diſcourſe of Sickneſs and Reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, <hi>page 97.</hi>
               </note> O how vaſtly different is that Aſſembly from ſuch a one as this! Here we are with our unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, with our Fears, with our ſtrong Corruptions, and with our many Sins; whereas they are all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and compleat in Holineſs. We ſhall then be no more diſturbed with the Abuſes of the Wicked, we ſhall be no more griev'd with their Oaths and Curſes, nor trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with their Company, but be in the happy Society of thoſe that will delight us, and ſuch as to Eternity we ſhall enjoy; and not only ſhall our Souls enjoy theſe Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licities,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.21.</note> but at the Reſurrection our Bodies ſhall be joyn'd to them, and both ſhall be happy: Our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ſhall not be what now they are, foul, unactive Lumps of Clay,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Silve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi>'s Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in the Supplement to the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe.</note> they are now pierced with Cold, and worn with Labours, appaled with Griefs and Dangers, and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:97103:26"/> grip'd with Pains, and macerated with keen and envious Paſſions, and after all, mouldred to Duſt by Death and Rottenneſs; but there neither Deformity, Pains, nor Death, ſhall be their fear nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe. Thus have I briefly ſhew'd you what this Reward is, that that thoſe ſhall obtain that run, as I have ſhown you, in this Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Race, and the Happineſſes, the Felicities, the Glories that there they ſhall injoy. And after all, I muſt conclude ſomewhat like the Apoſtle, That <hi>eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>neither hath it entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the heart of man fully to conceive of the things that God hath prepar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in heaven for them that love him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having now done what I promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as to the Doctrinal part, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the Application.</p>
            <p>Is it ſo then, that the greateſt Speedineſs and Celerity in the Ways
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:97103:26"/> of God, muſt be conſtantly practiſed by thoſe that would obtain everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Life? Then,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> From hence we may draw a Uſe of Reproof for thoſe Perſons that are creeping (as it were) to Heaven, inſtead of running ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; that go as if they did not care whether they came there or no, or as if they had an Eternity of Time allow'd them for their Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. What do you mean, <hi>Sirs?</hi> Your Sun is ſetting, the Night draws on, the Shadows of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening have overtaken you, ſtir up your ſelves, O ſlothful Souls, you are upon the very Borders of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; your Lives are but as a Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour,<note place="margin">James 4.14.</note> and what will become of your Souls, if your day is gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your work be done? Are you not aſhamed to ſee ſo many over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take you? Are you not aſham'd to make no further progreſs, that have ſo many helps provided for
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:97103:27"/> you, and tender'd to you? Are you not aſham'd that God ſhould ſee you loytering by the way? Are you not aſham'd that every trivial matter ſhould ſtop you? O for ſhame caſt away all your hindran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, get rid of your Obſtructions, and run; you'll be be-lated, O Souls! Don't you ſee what haſte Sinners make to Hell? Shall they ſtrive and run for Damnation, more than you for Salvation? O take this timely Reproof, you lazy, ſlothful ones. What will become of you, if you ſhall idle till Chriſt calls you to an account? How will that word ſound in your ears,<note place="margin">Matth. 25.26.</note> 
               <hi>Thou wicked and ſlothful ſervant.</hi> The true cauſe of thy neglect, is thy ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, and not thy Inability; and when that follows, Verſe 30. <hi>Caſt ye the unprofitable ſervant into utter dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> throw him into Hell, let him ſee my Face no more. Then will you wiſh (tho too late) that you had been ſpeedy in your Courſe,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:97103:27"/> that you had improv'd your Time and Talents, but then no more Time, nor Talents will be granted; then you are undone to Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Are you Young? Therefore do you loyter? Do you not ſee Young die as well as Old? Have you not a proof of this now before your Eyes? Are you in Health and Strength? Therefore do you loyter? Don't you ſee as ſtrong as the ſtrongeſt of you, and as healthy as the moſt health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, ſuddenly ſnatched away. O therefore loyter no longer, begin now to be ſpeedy, leſt an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after be never granted. <hi>Behold!</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.2.</note> 
               <hi>now is the accepted time! behold, now is the day of ſalvation.</hi> This Life is the time wherin your Calling and Election muſt be made ſure. This Life is the time wherein you muſt <hi>work out your Salvation with fear and trembling.</hi> This Life is the time wherein you muſt be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the Kingdom of Grace, if ever you expect to be admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:97103:28"/> the Kingdom of Glory. This Life is the time wherein you muſt run with ſpeed and patience, the Race that is ſet before you, if ever you expect to receive that great and glorious Reward that is prepared for ſuch as are ſpeedy, conſtant, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere in their Courſe: O, therefore mend your pace, leſt you ſhould be be-lated to Heaven.</p>
            <p>Let a ſecond Uſe, be a Uſe of Advice, and that to two ſorts of Perſons. <hi>Firſt,</hi> To thoſe that having begun and continued for a time, are now drawing back. I adviſe you that have begun to run in this Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Race, to hold on, and that to the end; 'twill be your own ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day; will not theſe Promiſes allure you;<note place="margin">Matth. 10.22.</note> 
               <hi>He that endureth to the end, ſhall be ſaved.</hi> Can you deſire a better Reward for your Pains than Salvation? 'Tis no wonder if at any time we ſee a poor Sinner draw back from ſerving the Devil; for
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:97103:28"/> he may well grow weary of his work, becauſe of his wages;<note place="margin">Rom. 6.23.</note> he'll be dreadfully Rewarded. But indeed it may be admired at, to ſee any turn their backs upon God, and grow weary of his Service, who will be ſo well rewarded, greatly above what they do deſerve. To ſee Perſons turn their backs upon Salvation, we may admire at their Folly and Madneſs; what think you of that other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe? <hi>Be thou faithful unto death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 2.10</note> 
               <hi>and I will give you a crown of life,</hi> or an unfaidable Crown of Glory, as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.4:</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Sirs,</hi> you that are weary of Gods ways, that grow tired of that which will (if you continue therein) end in your eternal Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; produce ſuch a Promiſe as this from the World, Sin or Satan, if you can; no, they have no ſuch Reward; pray then be perſwaded to hold on, to perſevere. <hi>Sirs,</hi> you can't ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine the miſery you'll bring upon your ſelves, by drawing back; you'll
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:97103:29"/> incur God's hatred, and you had better have the hatred of the whole World.<note place="margin">Hebr. 10.38.</note> Read and conſider; reſolve therefore whatever comes on't, to hold out to the end, that ſo you may be happy. But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Let it be a Uſe of Advice to the Hypocrites; you have heard how far a Hypocrite may go, and yet be rotten at heart; and you have heard ſomething of the heinouſneſs of Sin; and the puniſhment that will follow. I do now adviſe you, if you tender your Souls good, to go no further in ſuch a ſtate and condition, for you'll be damn'd for your pains: O whatever you do, be upright; let God have your hearts in all your Actions; make us no longer believe that you are what you are not, for 'tis you that will be the loſers at laſt. Read that Scripture often, and I leave you at this time, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.20. Chriſt tells you plainly, That <hi>except your righteouſneſs exceed the righteouſneſs of the Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:97103:29"/> ye ſhall in no wiſe enter into the kingdom of heaven.</hi> Now what was their Righteouſneſs? Why truly, 'twas an outſide Righteouſneſs; they were <hi>very Hypocrites,</hi> as Chriſt often calls them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.13, 14, 15. and in many more places. And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if any thing moves to Sincerity, it will be the thoughts of the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Hypocriſy. But then</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Let us take up an Uſe of Lamentation, and that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of thoſe poor Souls, that inſtead of running in the ways of God that lead to Heaven, they are running head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to Hell: Poor Souls! don't you tremble to think of your end; methinks my heart bleeds for you! O join with me, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, in my ſorrow for theſe poor Souls! Lord, what a Grief muſt it needs be to any compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate heart, to think of their ſad Condition! O that poor crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:97103:30"/> ſhould with ſuch delight work out their own ruin! O that they will be their own butchers, not of their bodies, but (which is worſe) of their precious Souls! Who can forbear to weep, to ſee ſinners go cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to Hell! O that Chriſt and his Grace ſhould be ſlighted by them that have ſo much need of both! O that overtures of Reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation ſhould be refuſed by ſuch as are juſt dropping into Hell, into the midſt of Everlaſting Burnings! Lord pity them! Lord open their eyes! O that they might ſee their danger, before they feel it; that ſo they might timely turn back, and eſcape it, that we may have cauſe to rejoice in thy Mercy towards them!</p>
            <p>One Uſe more, and that ſhall be of Comfort to the godly, to thoſe that run ſpeedily, conſtantly, and ſincerely in the ways of God. Lift up your heads with comfort, for
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:97103:30"/> you are happy ſouls, you are in the way of your duty, and you ſhall be rewarded; tho your Race be toilſome to the fleſh, let the Reward that will follow upon your continuing ſtedfaſt to the end, be your Cordial and Comfort. Conſider; 'Tis but a little while, and all your labour will be over,<note place="margin">Rev. 14.13.</note> and you ſhall have an Eternal Reſt. Do you object by way of Complaint, I ſuffer ſo much by reaſon of many and great Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and Troubles, and by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of God's taking away my Comforts, my Children, my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and Friends, that I find my ſelf greatly hindred in my way to Heaven; and I fear that I ſhall not hold out long; I doubt I ſhall not perſevere to the end.</p>
            <p>I ſhall endeavour to anſwer you fully, and ſo cloſe: You muſt then believe this as a great truth, That Afflictions muſt of neceſſity
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:97103:31"/> come upon thoſe that run in this Heavenly Race; nay, 'tis impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be freed from them; <hi>all that will live godly in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus muſt ſuffer Perſecution;</hi> for <hi>whom God loves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>he chaſtens; and ſcourges every ſon whom he receives.</hi> We are Baſtards, and not Sons, if we are free from Affliction. Thoſe Beaſts that are appointed for the Slaughter, are let run in Fat Paſtures; but thoſe that are not appointed for ſuch an end, are daily wrought, and ſubject to the yoke: The Stones that were for <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Building,<note place="margin">1 Kings 7.9.</note> were ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and hewn before they were laid therein; and ſo muſt every Chriſtian be ſquared and hewn too, by Affliction, that is to be a lively Stone in this Spiritual Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">Pſal. 118.22.</note> of which Chriſt Jeſus is the Head Corner-Stone. The Lord ſpareth ſome for a time, that he may puniſh them for ever; and he chaſtens ſome for a time, that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:97103:31"/> he may ſpare them for ever: <hi>Dives,</hi> that was ſpared on earth, was tormented in Hell; and <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> that was afflicted on earth, was received into Heaven.<note place="margin">Luk. 16.19. ad fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</note> He that would reign with Chriſt in the Kingdom of Glory, muſt ſuffer for him in the vale of Tears. He that would obtain Chriſt, muſt follow him; and he that does follow him, muſt do it with his Croſs. Chriſt ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before he entred into Glory; and ſo muſt Chriſtians before they can be glorified. Surely the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant muſt not be above his Maſter. If we ſuffer, we ſhall reign: We muſt not expect to drink of thoſe Rivers of Pleaſures, that run through the Celeſtial Paradice, unleſs we are willing to drink of the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Cup of Affliction: Many are the Troubles of the Righteous; one affliction ſeldom comes alone, for God is not like the waſp, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſtung once, can ſting no more,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:97103:32"/> but there is a plurality of Croſſes with God, he can ſting agen and agen. As one ſorrowful meſſenger came to <hi>Job</hi> after another, even ſo one affliction viſiteth the Chriſtian after another. Thoſe therefore that run in the race of Godlineſs, muſt not think this ſtrange, neither muſt they think to be free from affliction. Thus you ſee that of neceſſity afflictions muſt come upon the people of God, upon thoſe that run in this Heavenly race. You ſay further, that God takes away your Comforts, your Children, your Relations, your Friends, and this makes you fear you ſhall not hold on, but rather draw back. In anſwer to this, conſider, Hath God dealt worſe with you than with others of his Children that have been as precious in his ſight as you, and have done as much for his Glory. Pray compare your caſe with <hi>Job</hi>'s, read that Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſeriouſly at your leiſure, you'l there find that God depriv'd him of all his outward Comforts, and of his
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:97103:32"/> Children too; and (bleſſed be God) he hath not dealt ſo ſeverely with you, you have yet a great many bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and comforts, that God is yet pleaſed to continue to you,<note place="margin">Job 1.</note> and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly as to Children. God has not taken your All, and can't you ſpare God one Lamb or two out of your Flock without repining. Obſerve what <hi>Job</hi> ſays, when depriv'd of all his outward Comforts, <hi>The Lord gave,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 1.21.</note> 
               <hi>and the Lord hath taken away, bleſſed be the name of the Lord:</hi> He acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges him to be both good and juſt in all his ways, and bleſſeth him for all, whether giving or taking. O do you learn <hi>Job</hi>'s ſpirit.</p>
            <p>But by this time you may readily ask, what reaſons can be given for God's thus ſuffering his Children to be afflicted? I anſwer, there are many reaſons that may be given for this; I ſhall give you a few of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God ſuffers his Children to be afflicted, that he might wean them from the love of this world; which
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:97103:33"/> we are naturally prone to dote upon, but eſpecially in a proſperous ſtate; then we are apt and ready to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getful of God, and of our ſelves too, then the weeds are ready to overgrow the corn, and the fleſh ready to domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neer over the ſpirit; but by affliction we are brought to hate that which before we loved, and to embrace that which before we loathed. In time of proſperity we are apt to pride our ſelves in our worldly enjoyments, in our Goods and Poſſeſſions, and to have high and lofty thoughts of our ſelves, as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> Dan. 4.30. <hi>Is not this great Babylon that I have built for the houſe of the Kingdom, by the might of my power, and for the honour of my Majeſty?</hi> But when the Lord takes him to task, making of him to live with the beaſts of the field, and to eat graſs like oxen, then he was brought to acknowledg one above him,<note place="margin">Dan. 4.37.</note> to acknowledg that he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to abaſe all thoſe that walk in pride. By dealing thus with us, he
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:97103:33"/> brings us experimentally to know, that the world and the things thereof are vanity, and that they are at his diſpoſal to give and take away at his pleaſure. Thus therefore does God ſuffer his Children to be afflicted, that he might withdraw their affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions from the fading vanities of the world.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2ly,</hi> To draw us to amendment of life;<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.67.</note> 
               <hi>Before I was afflicted</hi> (ſays the Pſalmiſt) <hi>I went aſtray, but now have I kept thy Word.</hi> Affliction was the cauſe of his reformation; when we ſin, and go on therein, then God out of love ſtrikes us with the rod of affliction, to cauſe us to remember our ſins, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of them. The affliction of the Body many times proves whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Phyſick for the ſoul; though it wounds the outward man, it many times renews the inward man. God can't endure to ſee the ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh of ſin upon the faces of his Children, but he preſently waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:97103:34"/> it off with the water of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3ly,</hi> God ſuffereth his Children to be afflicted, that they might the more earneſtly call upon him, and the more ſpeedily ſeek unto him. 'Tis hard to keep ſilence when in grievous pain. Affliction makes us run to God for help and releaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;<note place="margin">Jon. 2.</note> thus did <hi>Jonah</hi> when in the Whale. Our requeſts are then commonly more earneſt and fervent; how earneſt are they in their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs!<note place="margin">Jon. 1.14.</note> 
               <hi>We beſeech thee, Lord, we beſeech thee.</hi> Thus therefore does God many times oppreſs us, that we might cry unto him; crying un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, he might hear us; and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us, might deliver us; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering us, he might be glorified of us.</p>
            <p n="4">4. For the exerciſe of their Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as Faith, Hope, Love, Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Patience, and Humility.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Faith is exerciſed in Affliction, by conſidering the cauſes of God's
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:97103:34"/> Permiſſion, and believing moſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly his Promiſes concerning our Deliverance: We look by an Eye of Faith beyond all outward Helps and Means, to that unſeen Hand of Power that is able and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to deliver us; and we believe and know it ſhall be ſo, becauſe of his Word.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hope; By aſſuring our ſelves of the Rewards promiſed to thoſe that ſuffer patiently; hope keeps our hearts from breaking, and it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a well-grounded hope, 'tis (when exerciſed) in the greateſt affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions comfortable.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Love is exerciſed in affliction, by conſidering the love of Chriſt in ſuffering for us, and thereby we are engaged to ſuffer for him again.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Obedience; by conforming our wills to the will of God. Muſt I ſuffer? well, ſays the ſoul, I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, ſeeing it is my Father's plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; I freely ſubmit, becauſe my
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:97103:35"/> Lord has taught me ſo to do; and in obedience to God's will, the ſoul will ſubmiſſively ſay, Not my will, but thine be done; tho it be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo contrary to nature, tho never ſo hard to bear. In the greateſt afflictions the Child of God will ſubmiſſively ſay, Lord, this is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to what thou didſt undergo for me.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Patience is exerciſed in affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, by ſuffering quietly, willingly, and cheerfully. Thus was the Lord pleaſed to exerciſe <hi>Job</hi>'s Patience; and although God had permitted Satan to tempt him,<note place="margin">Job 1.</note> his enemies to undo him, his Children by ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den death to be taken from him, his body to be afflicted with boils and ſores, having no part free from pain and grief; his Wife to be an occaſion of offence unto him, which in theſe diſtreſſes ſhould have been a comfort; yet notwithſtanding all this, <hi>Job</hi> ſin'd not againſt his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:97103:35"/> Thus was the Patience of the Apoſtles, and Martyrs, tried and exerciſed, namely, by and in Affliction, who were ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing impatient, and from murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that they quietly and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully laid down their Lives for the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Humility, by abaſing our ſelves in the ſight of God, acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that theſe Sufferings, theſe Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, are nothing in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Hell, which for our Sins we have deſerved; tho our Affliction may be many times more than we are able to bear, yet it is not ſo much as we do deſerve.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> The Lord ſuffereth his People to be afflicted, that the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Power, and the infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Mercy might be ſhown in the delivery of us. You read, that when the Diſciples ask'd our Saviour the reaſon why the Man
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:97103:36"/> was born blind: He tells them, <hi>Not for his own ſins, nor for the ſins of his parents, but that the works of God ſhould be made manifeſt in him,</hi> John 9.2, 3. from which we may truly gather thus much, That the Man was born blind, that Chriſt might have occaſion to ſhew the greatneſs of his Power in reſtoring his ſight. So 'tis ſaid of <hi>Lazarus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 11.4.</note> that he died to this end, <hi>that God might be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied</hi> in raiſing him from the dead. Thus have I ſhewn you for what reaſons God ſuffereth his People to be afflicted. Now from all that hath been ſaid, we may ſee, that Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions are rather helps, than hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drances to us in this Heavenly Race; therefore be not diſcouraged be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of Afflictions, for the Lord in his due time will deliver you out of them all; rather pray that God would ſanctify your Afflictions, than remove them; and endeavour to arm your ſelves <hi>with the whole armour of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.13.</note> that ſo you may not by reaſon
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:97103:36"/> of Satan's Temptations, and the prevalency of your own Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, fall under them. And ſeeing Afflictions are ſo convenient for us, let us learn to bleſs God for them; for had it not been for theſe, we might have been yet (for ought we know) in love with the World and Sin, which at laſt would have brought us to Hell. Thus (by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Aſſiſtance) have I ſpoken what I deſign'd on this Subject. O that God would now be pleaſed to make it effectual for you Souls good, for the ſtirring of you up to be more ſpeedy, conſtant, and ſincere in running your Race. O that at the Day of Judgment, I might meet you all that are here this day, at the Right Hand of Jeſus Chriſt, which will be an aſſurance to us of our entring into Glory; for 'tis to theſe he will ſay,<note place="margin">Matth. 25.34.</note> 
               <hi>Come ye bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of my Father, inherit the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom prepared for you, from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the world.</hi> Now, the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:97103:37"/> time that remains, let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to improve, by being more ſpeedy, conſtant, and ſincere in run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our Race. O let us <hi>be ſtedfaſt, unmovable,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.58.</note> 
               <hi>always abounding in the work of the Lord, foraſmuch as we know that our labour ſhall not be in vain in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:97103:37"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
